Guide to the First Congregational Church of Ithaca records, 1830-1946.
First Congregational Church of Ithaca records,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
First Congregational Church of Ithaca records, 1830-1946.
3910
First Congregational Church of Ithaca.
2 cubic ft.
Lists, reports, records, constitution, bulletins, and other documents.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Records include membership lists; lists of pew holders; reports of trials of church members and disciplinary actions taken; baptismal records; constitution; annual reports; treasurer's reports; records of marriages and deaths; reports of meetings of the Board of Elders; petition and resolution concerning separation fron the Protestant Reformed Dutch Church of Ithaca, New York; and bound volumes of church bulletins.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Records include membership lists; lists of pew holders; reports of trials of church members and disciplinary actions taken; baptismal records; constitution; annual reports; treasurer's reports; records of marriages and deaths; reports of meetings of the Board of Elders; petition and resolution concerning separation fron the Protestant Reformed Dutch Church of Ithaca, New York; and bound volumes of church bulletins.
SUBJECTS
Names:
First Congregational Church of Ithaca.; Protestant Reformed Dutch Church (Ithaca, N.Y.).
Subjects:
Religion--New York (State)--Ithaca.; Ithaca (N.Y.)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Access to records dated subsequent to 1937 is restricted to those with written permission of the Church Clerk or Council President or Chairman of the Trustees.
CONTAINER LIST
- Title: Church Record (applied label: 1830-1864 ), 1 (Box 1)
  Description: Leader boun record book, 8 1/2" x 10 3/4", handwritten in ink, first 140 pages paginated in pencil.
  Contents:
  Report of meeting of members of First Presbyterian Church and Congregation of the Village of Ithaca, (day and month omitted) 1880.
  Resolution of withdrawal from the Presbyterian Church.
  Chronological record of meetings of the Consistory of the Protestant Reformed Dutch Church of Ithaca, also meetings of male members of the church, of committees, and of the Church. Included are copies of important letters, resolutions, lists of pew holders, reports of trials of members and disciplinary action taken. Apr. 3, 1830-Dec. 2, 1863.
  Chronological list of members of the Protestant Reformed Dutch Church, Ithaca, Apr. 2, 1830-Aug. 4, 1865. Includes when and how they were received, when and how they left.
  Register of Marriages by Pastors of the Reformed Dutch Church, Ithaca, Feb. 10, 1831-Mar. 13, 1866, also one marriage recorded for Nov. 6, 1872, 19 pp.
  Register of Infants and Children baptized in the Reformed Dutch Church, July 10, 1830-Dec. 27, 1864, 16 pp.
  On last page, anonymous comment on reasons for withdrawal from the Presbyterian Church.
  Notes:
  One page torn out between meetings of Dec. 12, 1838 and Apr. 20, 1839.
  Following list of members are several blank pages, last two pages cut out.
- Title: First Church of Christ in Ithaca Roll of Members 1830-1879, 2 (Box 1)
  Description: Leather bound record book, 9 1/2" x 11", handwritten in ink, page numbers in pencil.
  List of Pastors, Mann to Tyler.
  Chronological numered list of members, Apr. 2, 1830 (No. 1) to Nov. 23, 1879 (No. 776). States when and how they were received, when and how they left.
- Title: None (applied label: 1830-1889 ), 3 (Box 1)
  Thin record book, 8 1/2" x 13 3/4", alphabetized pages, handwritten in ink by one person.
  Contents: Alphabetical list of members, 1831-1882.
- Title: Records R.D.C. (applied label: 1853-1881 ), 4 (Box 1)
  Description: Leather bound record book, 9" x 13", handwritten in ink.
  Contents: Chronological record of meetings of Consistory; Board of Elders; Minister, Elders and Deacons; Male Members of Church; Members of Church; Trustees (after 1873); Church Council. Included are annual reports, treasurer's reports, membership statistics, lists of pewholders, letters of dismission, members received, baptisms, etc. Also included are copies of important letters, reports of installation of pastors, Resolution of Withdrawal from Reformed Dutch Church (Dec. 23, 1872), establishment of Board of Trustees (Feb. 19, 1873), Articles of Faith, adopted Oct. 1, 1874, Constitution of First Church of Christ - Congregational of Ithaca, N.Y. adopted Mar. 1880. (First meeting Dec. 30, 1853, last meeting Oct. 25, 1893.) [Baptisms appear in minutes.]
  There is a time gap between meeting reports of Mar. 7, 1870 and Dec. 23, 1872.
  Several pages cut out in Church Council report of Dec. 18, 1874, continuity of report is continued in darker ink. Two pages cut out between June 28, 1881 and June 29, 1881, no apparent lack of continuity.
- Title: Records R.P.D.C. Ithaca (applied label: 1860-1880 ), 5 (Box 1)
  Description: Leather bound record book, 9" x 14", handwritten in ink.
  Chronological list of members as corrected and revised on May 27, 1866 with membership number and date of reception. Apr. 2, 1830 (No. 1) to Aug. 4, 1865 (No. 162).
  Chronological numbered list of members received during the pastorate of Rev. Strong, with date of reception. Sept. 1866 (No. 1) to Sept. 30, 1871 (No. 60).
  Alphabetical list of members received after May 27, 1866 to 1871 stating when and how they were received, when and how they left.
  A list of Baptisms of Adults and Children, Dec. 25, 1859 to Sept. 30, 1871, 4 pp.
  Record of Marriages, Oct. 4, 1866 to May 3, 1882, 12 pp.
  Record of Deaths, Aug. 31, 1866 to Dec. 2, 1871, 2 pp.
- Title: None (applied label: 1866-1872 ), 6 (Box 1)
  Description: Thin bound record book, 8 1/2" x 13", handwritten in ink.
  Contents: Reports of Meetings of the Board of Elders of the Reformed Protestant Dutch Church of Ithaca, N.Y. Aug. 25, 1866 to Dec. 7, 1872
- Title: Church Records 1872-1917, 7 (Box 1)
  Description: Bound record book (front cover replaced), 8 1/2" x 10 3/4", handwritten in ink, typed or printed sheets pasted in.
  Chronological reports of meetings of Trustees, also meetings of Congregation, Corporation and annual meetings of Trustees and Society. Includes copy of petition to separate from Reformed Dutch Church with list of persons signing; Bylaws of Board of Trustees (1881); Articles of Association between Corporation and Church (1881). Period between 1881 and 1884 devoted largely to financing and building the new church.
- Title: Church Clerk's Records ( May 22, 1893-Jan. 26, 1938 ), 8 (Box 1)
  Description: Leather bound record book, 8 3/4" x 11 3/4" x 3 3/4", printed page numbers, handwritten in ink, many printed or typed pasted inserts.
  Title Sheet: Minutes of the Consistory and Records of Congregational Meetings - First Congregational Church in Ithaca, N.Y. Beginning with the pastorate of Rev. Wm. Elliot Griffis, D.D.
  Alphabetized list of members indexed to page numbers referring to them.
  Chronological record of various meetings (except trustees), annual meetings of Church and Society, letters, financial reports, etc. Much related typed or printed material is included. Also recorded are admissions and departures of members, baptisms, and deaths (often with newspaper obituaries pasted in).
  Most of the records in this book were kept by L.E. Patterson, Church Clerk for over forty years.
  Access to records dated subsequent to 1937 restricted to the written permission of the Church Clerk or Council President or Chairman of the Trustees.
- Title: Trustee Minutes 1917-1930, 9 (Box 1)
  Description: Bound record book (poor binding), 8 1/4" x 14", printed page numbers, handwritten in ink with some typed records pasted in.
  Minutes of Church Meeting, May 23, 1917.
  Minutes of trustee meetings, May 27, 1917 to July 19, 1930. Includes trustees meeting with Advisory Board, with Consistory, and reports of annual meetings of Church.
- Title: Trustee Minutes ( Oct. 7, 1930-May 6, 1946 ), 10 (Box 2)
  Description: Bound record book, 8 1/4" x 14 1/4" x 2", handwritten in ink to page 10, typed sheets pasted in later.
  Minutes of trustee meetings. Includes treasurer's reports, budgets, related letters, and miscellaneous material.
- Bound Volumes of Church Bulletins
  - Congregational Church Bulletins, 1926-1927 (Box 2)
  - Congregational Services, 1927-1928 (Box 2)
  - Congregational Calendars, 1928-1929 (Box 2)
  - Congregational Services, 1929-1930 (Box 2)
  - Congregational Services, 1930-1931 (Box 2)
  - First Congregational Church, 1931-1932 (Box 2)
  - Church Programs, 1932-1933 (Box 2)
  - Church Programs, 1933-1934 (Box 2)
  - Congregational Programs, 1937-1938 (Box 2)
- Sets of Church Bulletins Pasted Together
  - Apr. 20-Dec. 28, 1919 (Box 2)
  - Jan. 4-July 11, 1920 (Box 2)
  - Sept. 26, 1920-Apr. 24, 1921 (Box 2)
  - May 8-June 12, 1921 (Box 2)
  - Sept. 18, 1921-Apr. 9, 1922 (Box 2)
  - May 14-June 18, 1922 (Box 2)
  - Sept. 17-Dec. 17, 1922 (Box 2)
  - Christmas Bulletin - Dec. 24, 1922 (Box 2)
  - Dec. 31, 1922-June 17, 1923 (Box 2)
  - Sept. 16, 1923-June 15, 1924 (Box 2)
  - Sept. 14-Dec. 14, 1924 (Box 2)
  - Christmas Bulletin - Dec. 21, 1924 (Box 2)
  - Several loose copies of Easter Day, Apr. 2, 1926 containing resignation statement of Rev. Condit. (Box 2)